{
  "reference_number": "11449",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a 2050 target in legislation now",
      "answer_index": 0,
      "notes": "However I support a more ambitious target of net zero by 2040."
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Emissions - Net zero emissions across all greenhouse gases by 2050",
      "answer_index": 1,
      "notes": "I support the most ambitious target: reducing greenhouse gases to net zero by 2050, but would prefer a 2040 target if possible. I\n also support taking a science-based approach to ensure our efforts to reduce emissions are as impactful as possible: we should aim\n\n for negative levels of long-lived gases, while reducing short-lived gases to sustainable levels."
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions only (including from new forest planting)",
      "answer_index": 7,
      "notes": "The New Zealand net zero carbon target should be met by domestic reductions only. However New Zealand has international\n responsibilities and should be supporting and assisting in mitigation and adaptation in developing countries through mechanisms\n\n such as additional aid or perhaps purchasing carbon credits. Emphasis should be placed on reducing fossil fuel based emissions as\n soon as possible. The Zero Carbon Act should also provide a framework for transparency and accountability around New Zealand's\n international climate finance"
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "The 2050 target should not be altered in response to “economic changes” as this undermines its long-term certainty. However, the\n\n ability to revise the 2050 target to be more ambitious, in light of major changes in scientific understanding or international\n agreements should be permitted."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "I agree with 5-year budgets set 10-15 years in advance, so that three are in effect at all times."
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "No - emissions budgets should not be able to be changed",
      "answer_index": 9,
      "notes": "Emissions budgets should not be altered in response to “economic changes” as this undermines their long-term certainty. However,\n the ability to revise the 2050 target to be more ambitious, in light of major changes in scientific understanding or international\n agreements should be permitted."
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "this undermines their long-term certainty. However, the ability to revise the 2050 target to be more ambitious, in light of major\nchanges in scientific understanding or international agreements should be permitted."
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "I agree that the Government and the Climate Commission should take the following factors into consideration when advising on and\nsetting budgets: • scientific knowledge regarding climate change • technology relevant to climate change • economic\n\ncircumstances and the likely impact of a decision on the economy, as well as the competitiveness of particular sectors of the\neconomy • fiscal circumstances and the likely impact of the decision on taxation, public spending and public borrowing • social\n\ncircumstances and the likely impact of a decision on fuel poverty • energy policy and the likely impact of a decision on energy\nsupplies and the carbon and energy intensity of the economy. We also need to consider our obligations under Te Tiriti o Waitangi as\n\nwell as Fairness (intergenerational justice and a just transition), cost-effectiveness, comprehensiveness and environmental\nsustainability."
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "We must learn from the mistakes of the UK's Climate Change Act and specify a strict time frame for producing a plan."
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "The Government’s policy plans to meet emission budgets should be comprehensive, fair, cost-effective, environmentally sustainable,\nand reflect a commitment to Te Tiriti o Waitangi. In setting plans to meet the emissions budgets, the government should be: •\n\nconsulting and working with Local Government to encourage them to mitigate and adapt to climate change • considering the relative\nconsumption emissions and other environmental impacts when weighing up mitigation and adaptation measures e.g. the emissions\ncost of producing electric cars overseas • considering the impact of its adaption and mitigation measures on other planetary\n\nboundaries i.e. biodiversity, nutrient pollution. • taking into account New Zealand’s contribution to international aviation and maritime\nemissions. • making sure they're based on the best science available • ensuring that they deliver fair outcomes for Kiwis • reflecting\n\nthe principle of a Just Transition for workers • honouring Te Tiriti o Waitangi • being environmentally sustainable, especially for New\nZealand's unique native plants and animals • maximising the impact of money spent and being cost-effective • encouraging\n\ninnovation • unlocking economic opportunities for New Zealanders, such as in renewable energy • honouring our international\ncommitments, including under the Paris Agreement • consulting people who may be economically affected, like farmers or\nbusinesses • consulting tangata whenua • consulting young people, who'll live to see more of the impact of climate change •\n\nconsulting communities already facing the physical impacts of climate change"
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "I believe that the Commission should not be a decision-making body. I support the Climate Commission having two functions 1.\nProviding expert advice and 2. Monitoring our progress and holding the government account. It should not be a decision-making\n\nbody as it would lead to a lack of democratic accountability, it becoming a comprised watch dog and that it would not have the ability\nto implement comprehensive policy plans."
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Advising the Government on policy settings in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 6,
      "notes": "The Commission should advise the Government on policy settings in the NZ ETS. It should not make decisions itself with respect to\nthe number of units available in the NZ ETS, or its implementation."
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "I agree with the following collective expertise: • climate change policy (including emissions trading) • resource economics and\n\nimpacts (including social impacts, labour markets and distribution) • te Tiriti o Waitangi, te reo me ona tikanga Māori and Māori\ninterests • climate and environmental science including mātauranga Māori • experience with addressing adaptation challenges like\nplanning, insurance and local government • risk management • engineering and/or infrastructure • community engagement and\n\ncommunications. • business competitiveness • knowledge of the public and private innovation and technology development system.\nI also think expertise in public health is also important. Consideration should be given to representation by young people, minority\n\ngroups and respected non-experts."
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "This may require a separate adaptation sub-committee within the Climate Commission."
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "I agree with the proposed functions below: • a national climate change risk assessment • a national adaptation plan • regular review\n\nof progress towards implementing the national adaptation plan • an adaptation reporting power Care will need to be taken in\nmanaging the interaction between national and local government roles."
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Yes. This would let the government and the public know about the risks to public and other infrastructure, and make these\norganisations better informed about the risks they face."
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "I am concerned about climate change and am very supportive of action to mitigate and adapt. As a Christian, I believe that we, as\n\npeople, have a call to care for God’s creation and to care for all peoples. This means supporting maximum ambition including meeting\nnet zero by 2040 domestically as well as supporting mitigation and adaption overseas especially with our Pacific neighbours. I am\nsupportive of taking action to limit warming to 1.5° C, since it has been those with privilege and opportunities who have made the\n\nmost out of fossil fuels, but it is those who have the least who will be the most disadvantaged by climate change. I believe that we\nneed to leave the world in a better place than it is now, and I think that this bill will help with that. We have a responsibility to the\n\ngenerations ahead, to do our utmost to turn this situation around. Although there will be pain involved, and no-one likes having to\nchange, there could be so many benefits in changing our current life styles... stronger communities, less meaningless consumption,\n\nmore mindful learning in general. New Zealand has this opportunity to showcase to the world what can be done if we pull together\nand if the government is brave enough and can display the leadership to make the necessary changes to our economy."
    }
  ]
}
